Hello everyone and welcome to EnglishPod.
大家好，欢迎来到EnglishPod。
My name is Marco.
我的名字是马可。
My name is Kathryn and we've been traveling around the world eating different foods from
我的名字是凯瑟琳，我们一直在环游世界，品尝各种不同的美食。
different countries and today we're in Thailand.
不同的国家，而今天我们来到了泰国。
That's right.
没错。
Thai food is one of the most popular types of food around the world especially because
泰国菜是世界上最受欢迎的美食之一，尤其因为
of that specific Asian taste it has.
那种独特的亚洲风味。
And so we're going to jump right into this dialogue today and see what we have prepared
那么我们今天就直接进入这段对话，看看准备了什么内容。
for you today.
今天为你准备的是。
What did you cook?
你做了什么菜？
Well, as you know, I was in Thailand last month and I took a cooking class.
嗯，你知道的，我上个月在泰国，参加了一个烹饪课。
So I prepared some of my favorite dishes.
所以我准备了一些我最喜欢的菜。
Great idea.
好主意。
As long as I don't get food poisoning.
只要我不会食物中毒就行。
So what is on the menu tonight?
今晚的菜单上有什么？
Okay, for starters we have Tom Yum soup.
好的，首先我们有冬阴功汤。
It's a bit spicy but really good.
有点辣，但真的很好吃。
This is delicious.
这个真好吃。
The ginger and lemongrass really give it a nice taste.
姜和柠檬草真的让这道菜味道很好。
Now this next dish is one of the most famous.
现在这道菜是最有名的之一。
Foreigners call it papaya salad but the proper name is Tom Sam.
外国人叫它木瓜沙拉，但正式名称是宋丹。
It is a spicy salad made from a mix of fresh vegetables including shredded unripened papaya
这是一种辛辣沙拉，由混合新鲜蔬菜制成，包括切碎的生木瓜
and tomato.
和番茄。
This is delicious.
这很好吃。
The combination of sour and spicy is really interesting.
酸辣的组合真的很有趣。
I could have this every day.
我可以每天都吃这个。
Okay, now for the last and best dish in my opinion.
好了，现在来说最后一道，也是我认为最好的一道菜。
This is called Pad Thai.
这叫泰式炒河粉。
Stir fried noodles with eggs, fish sauce, tamarind juice, red chili pepper plus bean
用鸡蛋、鱼露、罗望子汁、红辣椒和豆芽炒制的面条，
sprouts, shrimp and tofu garnished with crushed peanuts and coriander.
加上虾和豆腐，再撒上碎花生和香菜。
It's practically Thailand's national dish.
这几乎是泰国的国菜。
Wow, this is great.
哇，这太棒了。
I never knew Thai food was so creative and delicious.
我从不知道泰国菜这么有创意又好吃。
Want some more?
还想再来点吗？
I'm stuffed.
我吃饱了。
All right, so we've got a number of different dishes we'd like to talk about as well as
好了，我们有很多不同的菜肴想聊聊，还有
phrases.
一些短语。
So let's look at some of those dishes and important key words in language takeaway.
所以让我们看看语言要点中的一些菜肴和关键词。
Language takeaway.
语言要点。
All right, so the first word we have on language takeaway today is food poisoning.
好的，今天语言要点的第一个词是食物中毒。
So we don't want to get food poisoning when having this, any meal.
所以我们不想在吃这个的时候食物中毒，任何一餐都是。
Any meal, no, that's right.
任何一餐，不，没错。
Food poisoning is a bad thing.
食物中毒是件坏事。
Now this is something that happens when you eat bad food or dirty food.
这是当你吃了变质或不干净的食物时会发生的事情。
So you get very, very sick and you feel like you have to vomit, you have to throw up.
所以你会非常非常难受，感觉想呕吐，想吐出来。
That's right.
没错。
So your stomach hurts, you feel like you have to throw up, you may be going to the bathroom
所以你的胃疼，感觉想吐，可能还会频繁跑厕所。
very often.
非常频繁。
That means usually you have food poisoning.
那通常意味着你食物中毒了。
All right, and so people often associate food poisoning with food that you eat on the street,
好的，人们常常把食物中毒和你在街上吃的食物联系起来，
maybe dirtier food.
可能是更脏的食物。
But this is something you should be very careful of when you're traveling, not to Thailand
但这是你旅行时应该非常小心的事情，不只是泰国，
alone, but maybe to any other country.
可能任何其他国家都一样。
You can get it in America, you can get it in Mexico.
你在美国可能得，在墨西哥也可能得。
So just something to be careful of.
所以只是需要小心的事情。
That's right.
没错。
So apart from that, we're going to jump into our first dish for today.
所以除此之外，我们要进入今天的第一道菜了。
We're having a soup called Tom Yum Soup.
我们要喝一种叫冬阴功汤的汤。
Tom Yum Soup.
冬阴功汤。
Now this is one of my favorite soups.
这是我最喜欢的汤之一。
It's quite spicy, isn't it, Marco?
这道菜挺辣的，是吧，Marco？
Very spicy, but very, very good as well.
非常辣，但也非常非常好吃。
It has a kind of citric taste, like a lemon.
它有种柑橘的味道，像柠檬一样。
It does, and it's very yellow or orange colored.
确实，而且它颜色很黄或偏橙。
And it's a very, very common dish on Thai restaurant menus.
这是泰国餐厅菜单上非常非常常见的一道菜。
And there are some key ingredients in this soup that I think are important to discuss.
这道汤里有一些关键食材，我觉得值得讨论一下。
They're often found in Thai food and other kinds of Asian food.
它们经常出现在泰国菜和其他亚洲菜里。
The first one is ginger.
第一种是姜。
Ginger, that's right.
姜，没错。
This is a root.
这是一种根茎。
It kind of looks like a potato almost.
它看起来有点像土豆。
It does.
确实。
It's usually white and it has little arms, you know.
通常是白色的，而且有那种小分叉，你知道的。
It's not a round object.
它不是圆形的。
It's got pointy little arms.
它有尖尖的小分叉。
That's right.
没错。
And the characteristic taste of ginger is kind of strong and bitter.
姜的典型味道是又浓又苦。
It is quite strong.
确实很浓。
You'll find it in Japanese food.
你在日本菜里也能找到它。
Sometimes you get pickled ginger to eat.
有时候你会吃到腌制的姜。
It's like a pink food you get with sushi.
就像吃寿司时配的那种粉色食物。
Other times in Chinese cooking, it's something that's chopped up with garlic and cooked in
在中式烹饪中，它有时是和大蒜一起切碎后，
oil.
用油炒的。
So ginger is a very important one.
所以姜是一种非常重要的食材。
That's right.
没错。
So in this soup, we have ginger and we also have lemongrass.
所以在这道汤里，我们放了姜，还放了香茅。
So this is very interesting because it's not very easily found around the world.
这很有意思，因为它在世界各地不太容易找到。
That's right.
没错。
This is very common in Southeast Asian cooking.
这在东南亚烹饪中很常见。
And you might have a hard time finding it in places like America where it's not really
在美国这样的地方，你可能很难找到它，因为它并不是
a part of the cuisine.
当地饮食的一部分。
But lemongrass is very distinct.
但香茅非常独特。
It has a very strong flavor and it's actually quite long.
它的味道很浓，而且实际上相当长。
It's green and long.
它是绿色的，长长的。
It looks a bit like celery, but it's harder.
看起来有点像芹菜，但更硬。
That's right.
没错。
And the taste that it gives it is a little bit citric, kind of like a lemon almost.
它带来的味道有点柑橘味，几乎像柠檬一样。
That's right.
没错。
But you're going to find this in soups like tom yum or other things.
但你会在冬阴功汤之类的汤里找到它。
So lemongrass is another one.
所以香茅是另一种食材。
And then moving on to our next dish, which is one of the most, I think, the most popular
然后我们来看下一道菜，我认为这是泰国最受欢迎的
dishes of all Thailand is the famous pad thai.
菜肴之一，就是著名的泰式炒河粉。
Pad thai.
泰式炒河粉。
Now, this is absolutely my favorite Thai dish.
这绝对是我最喜欢的泰国菜。
And I know that's very cliche.
我知道这很老套。
It's something that everyone says, but it's true.
每个人都这么说，但这是真的。
You know, this is a great dish you can buy on the street.
你知道，这是一道很棒的菜，可以在街上买到。
You can buy it in a restaurant.
也可以在餐厅里买到。
It's basically a noodle dish, right?
它基本上是一道面条菜，对吧？
That's right.
没错。
It's stir fried noodles with eggs and peanuts are the most, like the key ingredients in
它是用鸡蛋和花生炒的面条，这是最关键的
there.
配料。
That's right.
没错。
But you might also get a little bit of hot red pepper, some sugar, some lime.
但你可能还会加一点红辣椒、一些糖、一些青柠。
And the noodles are flat.
面条是扁平的。
They're not round.
不是圆的。
That's right.
没错。
And actually one of the key ingredients also that gives it this very distinct taste is
实际上，给它带来这种独特味道的关键配料之一是
tamarind juice.
罗望子汁。
All right.
好的。
Tamarind juice.
罗望子汁。
This is again another one of those flavors from Southeast Asia that you might not find
这又是东南亚的一种风味，你在其他地方可能找不到，
in many other places, certainly not in America.
在美国肯定没有。
Now tamarind, they're funny looking things.
罗望子这东西长得挺滑稽的。
They look like peas, but they're dark brown.
它们看起来像豌豆，但颜色是深棕色的。
That's right.
没错。
So tamarind juice gives it this kind of sweet flavor.
所以罗望子汁给它带来了一种甜味。
So this is the interesting thing about pad thai is that you have these sweet flavors
所以泰式炒河粉的有趣之处在于，它有来自罗望子汁、
from the tamarind juice, from even the fish sauce combined with chili.
甚至鱼露和辣椒混合的甜味。
So it's kind of like a spicy, very sweet taste.
所以它有点像一种辣中带甜的味道。
And then you have citrus.
然后还有柑橘味。
You have some lime maybe and some sugar.
你可能加一些青柠和一些糖。
So it's a lot of different tastes and flavors, but it's a really magical combination.
所以有很多不同的味道和风味，但这真是一个神奇的组合。
That's right.
没错。
So that's all we have for language takeaway.
这就是我们语言学习的全部内容。
Why don't we take another listen to our dialogue?
我们不如再听一遍对话吧？
What did you cook?
你做了什么菜？
Well, as you know, I was in Thailand last month and I took a cooking class.
嗯，你知道，我上个月在泰国，参加了一个烹饪班。
So I prepared some of my favorite dishes.
所以我准备了一些我最喜欢的菜。
Great idea.
好主意。
As long as I don't get food poisoning.
只要我不会食物中毒就行。
So what is on the menu tonight?
那今晚的菜单是什么？
Okay.
好的。
For starters, we have Tom Yum soup.
开胃菜，我们有冬阴功汤。
It's a bit spicy, but really good.
有点辣，但真的很好吃。
This is delicious.
这很好吃。
The ginger and lemongrass really give it a nice taste.
姜和香茅真的给它带来了很好的味道。
Now this next dish is one of the most famous.
现在这道菜是最有名的之一。
Foreigners call it papaya salad, but the proper name is Tom Sam.
外国人叫它木瓜沙拉，但正式名称是宋丹。
It is a spicy salad made from a mix of fresh vegetables, including shredded unripened papaya
这是一种辛辣沙拉，由各种新鲜蔬菜混合而成，包括切碎的生木瓜
and tomato.
和番茄。
This is delicious.
这很好吃。
The combination of sour and spicy is really interesting.
酸辣的组合真的很有趣。
I could have this every day.
我可以每天都吃这个。
Okay.
好的。
Now for the last and best dish, in my opinion.
现在上最后一道，也是我认为最好的一道菜。
This is called Pad Thai.
这叫泰式炒河粉。
Stir fried noodles with eggs, fish sauce, tamarind juice, red chili pepper, plus bean
用鸡蛋、鱼露、罗望子汁、红辣椒、还有豆芽、
sprouts, shrimp, and tofu.
虾和豆腐炒的面条。
Garnished with crushed peanuts and coriander.
配上碎花生和香菜。
It's practically Thailand's national dish.
这几乎是泰国的国菜。
Wow.
哇。
This is great.
这太棒了。
I never knew Thai food was so creative and delicious.
我从来不知道泰国菜这么有创意又好吃。
Want some more?
还想再来点吗？
I'm stuffed.
我吃饱了。
All right.
好的。
We're back.
我们回来了。
So now let's take a look at four key phrases on Fluency Builder.
现在让我们看看流利度提升器里的四个关键短语。
Fluency Builder.
流利度提升器。
So first up we have the phrase on the menu.
首先，我们有短语“菜单上有什么”。
What's on the menu tonight?
今晚菜单上有什么？
That's right.
没错。
That person asked, so what's on the menu?
那个人问的是，菜单上有什么？
And by saying this, we're saying, well, what are we having for dinner?
说这个，其实是在问，我们晚餐吃什么？
What are we going to eat?
我们要吃什么？
That's right.
没错。
So you might want to think, okay, menu, I'm going to look at the menu, but you could even
你可能会想，菜单，我要看菜单，但你甚至
say this at home where there is no menu.
可以在家里没有菜单的时候说这个。
This is a spoken language way of saying, what are we eating tonight?
这是一种口语化的说法，意思是“我们今晚吃什么？”
Right.
对。
That's right.
没错。
What's for dinner?
晚餐吃什么？
What are we eating?
我们吃什么？
What's on the menu?
菜单上有什么？
Even though, as you said, there's no menu.
尽管，如你所说，没有菜单。
That's right.
没错。
And after that, we have another phrase that's really important.
之后，我们还有另一个非常重要的短语。
We say, for starters, we're going to have this or that.
我们说，作为开胃菜，我们要吃这个或那个。
So for starters.
所以是“作为开胃菜”。
That's right.
没错。
We said for starters, we are having a soup, a Tom Yum soup.
我们说过，作为开胃菜，我们喝汤，冬阴功汤。
So a starter dish is something that you have to begin the meal, a small dish maybe.
所以开胃菜是你开始用餐时吃的东西，可能是一小份菜。
That's right.
没错。
Start, starter.
开始，开胃菜。
So a starter is a noun, it's a thing, and it's something you eat at the beginning.
所以“开胃菜”是一个名词，是一个东西，是你一开始吃的东西。
Usually it's not very heavy.
通常不会很重。
A steak would never be a starter, right?
牛排永远不会是开胃菜，对吧？
Right.
对。
All right.
好的。
So here we have Tom Yum soup, which is our starter.
所以我们这里有冬阴功汤，这是我们的开胃菜。
And after that, we have the national dish.
之后，我们有国菜。
Now this is a great phrase.
这是一个很棒的短语。
Right.
对。
We had the Pad Thai, which is considered to be the national dish.
我们吃了泰式炒河粉，这被认为是国菜。
And so usually every country has their national dish, something that's unique or that a country
通常每个国家都有自己的国菜，一些独特或该国
is famous for.
著名的东西。
Like, for example, China would be famous for?
比如，中国以什么闻名？
Kung Pao chicken.
宫保鸡丁。
Kung Pao chicken, yeah.
宫保鸡丁，是的。
In America, you might even say that apple pie is the most important national dish.
在美国，你甚至可以说苹果派是最重要的国菜。
But do you guys have one in Ecuador?
但你们厄瓜多尔有国菜吗？
What's your national dish?
你们的国菜是什么？
I would say, I have no idea which would be.
我会说，我不知道哪个是。
It's not very well known.
不太出名。
Maybe ceviche is kind of shared between Peru and Ecuador.
也许酸橘汁腌鱼是秘鲁和厄瓜多尔共有的。
Like maybe in Argentina, you would say steak is a national dish.
比如在阿根廷，你会说牛排是国菜。
Yeah, absolutely.
是的，绝对。
Or in Mexico, you know, like tacos or enchiladas, stuff like that.
或者在墨西哥，你知道，像玉米卷或辣酱玉米饼之类的。
Or in Italy, spaghetti bolognese.
或者在意大利，意大利肉酱面。
That's right.
没错。
All right.
好的。
So we have a number of different countries and each country maybe has one or two national
所以我们有很多不同的国家，每个国家可能有一两个国菜。
dishes.
国菜。
These are very special dishes that are important for that country.
这些是非常特别的菜肴，对这个国家很重要。
That's right.
没错。
So we have our national dishes.
所以我们有我们的国菜。
And after we finish dinner, we ate so much that we say, I'm stuffed.
吃完晚餐后，我们吃了太多，所以会说“我吃饱了”。
I'm stuffed.
我吃饱了。
Now this is a common phrase that you will hear at the end of a meal when you've eaten
这是一个常见的短语，你会在吃完饭后听到，当你吃了
and eaten and eaten.
又吃又吃。
And it just means I'm full.
意思就是我饱了。
I'm full.
我饱了。
I can't eat anymore.
我不能再吃了。
Yeah, I'm stuffed.
是的，我吃饱了。
So stuffed means that I'm full of things.
所以“stuffed”意思是我塞满了东西。
Now it's a very informal way of saying I'm full, right?
这是一种非常非正式的说法，表示我饱了，对吧？
Because if somebody says, would you like some more soup?
因为如果有人问，你还想再来点汤吗？
You say, no, thank you.
你说，不了，谢谢。
I'm full.
我吃饱了。
Right.
对。
But if you're with friends, you can say, oh, I just had so much pizza.
但如果你和朋友在一起，你可以说，哦，我刚吃了好多披萨。
I'm stuffed.
我撑死了。
That's right.
没错。
So it's a little bit more informal, but a lot more native-like.
所以这稍微更随意一些，但更地道。
That's right.
没错。
All right.
好了。
So let's take a listen to our dialogue one last time.
那让我们最后听一遍对话。
What did you cook?
你做了什么菜？
Well, as you know, I was in Thailand last month and I took a cooking class.
嗯，你知道，我上个月在泰国，参加了一个烹饪课。
So I prepared some of my favorite dishes.
所以我准备了一些我最喜欢的菜。
Great idea.
好主意。
As long as I don't get food poisoning.
只要我不会食物中毒就行。
So what is on the menu tonight?
那今晚的菜单是什么？
OK, for starters, we have Tom Yum soup.
好的，开胃菜是冬阴功汤。
It's a bit spicy, but really good.
有点辣，但味道很好。
This is delicious.
这很好吃。
The ginger and lemongrass really give it a nice taste.
姜和柠檬草真的给它增添了好味道。
Now, this next dish is one of the most famous.
现在，下一道菜是最有名的之一。
Foreigners call it papaya salad, but the proper name is Tom Sam.
外国人叫它木瓜沙拉，但正式名称是宋丹。
It is a spicy salad made from a mix of fresh vegetables, including shredded unripened
这是一种辛辣的沙拉，由混合新鲜蔬菜制成，包括切碎的生
papaya and tomato.
木瓜和番茄。
This is delicious.
这很好吃。
The combination of sour and spicy is really interesting.
酸辣的组合真的很有趣。
I could have this every day.
我可以每天都吃这个。
OK, now for the last and best dish, in my opinion.
好了，现在上最后一道，也是我认为最好的一道菜。
This is called Pad Thai.
这叫泰式炒河粉。
It's stir fried noodles with eggs, fish sauce, tamarind juice, red chili pepper, plus bean
它是用鸡蛋、鱼露、罗望子汁、红辣椒，加上豆
sprouts, shrimp and tofu, garnished with crushed peanuts and coriander.
芽、虾和豆腐翻炒的河粉，再撒上碎花生和香菜点缀。
It's practically Thailand's national dish.
它几乎是泰国的国菜。
Wow, this is great.
哇，这太棒了。
I never knew Thai food was so creative and delicious.
我从来不知道泰国菜这么有创意又美味。
Want some more?
还想再来点吗？
I'm stuffed.
我吃饱了。
All right, so speaking of Thai food, it's very famous around the world, but it's very
好了，说到泰国菜，它在全世界都很有名，但它非常
spicy.
辣。
It can be very spicy, and what always surprises me about Thai food is that the salads might
它可以非常辣，而泰国菜总是让我惊讶的是，沙拉可能是
be the spiciest things on the menu.
菜单上最辣的东西。
People like to eat many different salads.
人们喜欢吃各种不同的沙拉。
You have a Chiang Mai chicken salad or you have a papaya salad, but these are really,
我们有清迈鸡肉沙拉或木瓜沙拉，但这些真的非常，
really spicy.
非常辣。
Yeah, that's right.
是的，没错。
We have a line in our dialogue that we're eating papaya salad, and it's very interesting
我们的对话里提到我们在吃木瓜沙拉，这很有趣，
because it has this fruit, papaya, and it has some other vegetables as well, but the
因为它含有这种水果——木瓜，还有一些其他蔬菜，但
salad is very, very spicy itself.
沙拉本身非常非常辣。
That's right, and you would never think of a fruit salad as being something that's spicy
没错，在美国你绝不会想到水果沙拉会是辣的，
in America.
在美国。
You'd think of it as being pretty tame, pretty boring.
你会觉得它很平淡，很无聊。
But that's what gives it a certain attraction to it, right?
但正是这点让它有了一种吸引力，对吧？
Absolutely, and I don't know if you're a big fan of Thai food.
当然，我不知道你是不是泰国菜的忠实粉丝。
I certainly am, and I really like that about Thai food, that you can have these really
我肯定是，而且我很喜欢泰国菜的一点是，你可以吃到这些非常
spicy dishes, but there's just so much flavor.
辣的菜，但味道却非常丰富。
There's so many things happening, lemongrass, sugar, lime, fish sauce.
有很多种味道交织在一起，比如柠檬草、糖、青柠、鱼露。
Yeah, it's very, very good.
是的，非常非常好吃。
And speaking of national dishes, this is actually a very interesting question because as we
说到国菜，这其实是个很有趣的问题，因为正如我们
mentioned, a couple of countries have national dishes like Italy and different places, but
提到的，有些国家有国菜，比如意大利和其他地方，但
what about in your country?
你们国家呢？
Do you have a national dish or what would you consider to be your national dish?
你们有国菜吗？或者你认为什么是你们的国菜？
That's right.
没错。
So we'd love to hear from you guys.
所以我们很期待听到你们的消息。
What's your national dish?
你们国家的国菜是什么？
Tell us all about it, what it tastes like, and even if there's some history, tell us
跟我们好好讲讲，它是什么味道，甚至如果有什么历史故事，也告诉我们
about that too.
那些历史。
Our website is EnglishPod.com.
我们的网站是 EnglishPod.com。
All right, we'll see you guys there.
好了，我们会在那里等你们。
Bye.
拜拜。
Bye, everybody, muah.
大家再见，么啊。